Guide to the American Youth Congress Records TAM.553
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Youth Congress Records
1938-1941
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Youth Congress
Lorne Bair Rare Books
TAM.553
3.5 Linear Feet in three record cartons and one manuscript box.
The American Youth Congress Records was an umbrella organization of United States youth advocacy groups, active from 1938-1941. Its intention was to unite these disparate groups under a single voice to promote opportunities for education and civic involvement for Depression-era youth, and to lobby on behalf of the under-21 population which at this time had no voting voice. The collection contains official correspondence, office files (financial reports, dunning letters from creditors, internal memoranda, etc.), and printed promotional material including brochures, posters, flyers, broadsides and fundraising material from a wide variety of pre-World War II youth organizations in the United States, Latin America and Europe.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Lorne Bair Rare Books in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.074.
Arrangement
The collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Historical/Biographical Note
The American Youth Congress (AYC) was established in 1935 as an umbrella organization of American youth advocacy groups. Its intention was to unite these disparate groups under a single voice to promote opportunities for education and civic involvement for Depression-era youth, and to lobby on behalf of the under-21 population. The AYC won the vocal support of First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt, and established itself as a powerful lobbying entity. Among many other causes, the AYC undertook lobbying efforts on behalf of racial justice, increased federal spending on education, and an end to mandatory participation in the Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) for male college students. In its final years, with WWII looming, the AYC fought a vigorous battle against the Conscription Act and advocated American neutrality in the war. From its inception the AYC followed a policy of inclusiveness, welcoming youth organizations of all political views to join and contribute. But as its membership grew (the AYC claimed to represent at least 4.5 million citizens in 1938), left-leaning groups such as the American Student Union and the Young Communist League began to comprise the largest block of members, and the leadership of the AYC became increasingly radicalized, until by 1940 many of its upper-level members, including Director Joseph Cadden and Secretary Joseph Lash, also claimed membership in Communist Party front organizations. The AYC came under frequent attack from the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) and particularly from the committee chairman Martin Dies, whose 1940 book The Trojan Horse in America was largely an exposé of Communist infiltration in the AYC ranks. Under the pressure of these HUAC attacks, and following its notorious anti-war, anti-Roosevelt rally on the White House lawn in 1940, the AYC lost the support of its few remaining political allies, including Eleanor Roosevelt; by 1941 its influence had all but waned, and the group was effectively disbanded by the end of that year.
Custodial History
Lorne Bair Rare Books purchased the American Youth Congress office files and correspondence in 2009 from a salvage company at a New York flea market. In 2010, Tamiment Library purchased the collection from Lorne Bair Rare Books.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents in detail the AYC's activities during its final four years (1938-1941), under the directorship of Frances Williams and, later, Joseph Cadden (the most frequent correspondent). It includes an extensive file of correspondence between Cadden and members of the Senate and House of Representatives on legislation including the Conscription Act, the continuing funding of the Civilian Conservation Corps, and support of the Neutrality Act. Of great interest are the extensive files of correspondence with member organizations ranging from municipal boys' clubs and the YMCA on the right, to the Student Union, the Southern Negro Youth Congress, International Labor Defense, and other radical or semi-radical organizations on the left. There is also an extensive file of correspondence relating to the organization of an International Youth Congress in 1941, including correspondence with dozens of youth organizations in Latin America and Europe; much of this correspondence is accompanied by examples of these foreign delegations' publications and promotional materials, most of which are extremely ephemeral newsprint or mimeograph productions. Nearly all are unabashedly anti-Fascist, pro-Marxist in tone and the collected result must represent a nearly unique accumulation of several hundred pieces of International leftist youth propaganda in the years prior to the Second World War. Finally, the archive includes several hundred internal documents, including invoices (often accompanied by increasingly urgent letters from creditors), memoranda, and printed materials reflecting the increasingly deteriorated state of the organization in its final waning years.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The collection contains a significant portion of fragile material, as well as some material that is housed in fragile folders, and these materials may require preservation measures prior to being made available for research.
Periodicals; Printed ephemera.; Newsletters.; Peace movements -- United States.; Financial records; Memorandums.; Correspondence.; Student movements -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Protest movements |z United States.; Reports.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; American Student Union; Cadden, Joseph; American Youth Congress; Southern Negro Youth Congress; International Youth Congress (1941); Lorne Bair Rare Books
- Congressional Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from [Joseph Cadden] to Senator Josh Lee, Sep 21, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Letter from [Joseph Cadden] to Senator Elbert D. Thomas, Oct 5, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from M. Gross secretary to Senator Lundeen to Joseph Cadden, Sep 30, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Pat Harrison, Oct 6, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from Joseph Cadden to Senator Alva B. Adams, Jan 16, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Vito Marcantonio, Jan 17, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Vito Marcantonio to Joseph Cadden, Jan 18, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Key Pittman, Jan 19, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Bruce Barton, Jan 17, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Bruce Barton to Joseph Cadden, Jan 19, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Joseph Cadden to Bruce Barton, Jan 23, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Lewis B. Schwellenbach, Jan 17, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Lewis B. Schwellenbach to Joseph Cadden, Jan 26, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Ernest Lundeen to Joseph Cadden, Jan 26, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Joseph Cadden to Ernest Lundeen, Jan 30, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Vito Marcantonio to Joseph Cadden, Jan 26, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative William H. Larrabee, Feb 2, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Norma Spelrein to Senator Elbert D. Thomas, Feb 7, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from T. Odon Mathews, acting clerk to Committee on Education and Labor, to William W. Hinckley, chairman of American Youth Congress, Feb 18, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Joseph Cadden to T. Odon Mathews, Feb 24, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Harry Seward secretary to Senator Pittman, Mar 10, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from George H. Seward (Harry Seward) to Joseph Cadden, Mar 14, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Key Pittman as suggested by Harry Seward, Mar 15, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Mrs. Edith N. Roger, Mar 15, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Lynn J. Frazier to Helen Hall, Mar 23, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Lynn J. Frazier, Mar 24, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Lynn J. Frazier to Joseph Cadden, Mar 28, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Lynn J. Frazier, Mar 30, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Key Pittman, Apr 7, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Senator Arthur Capper to American Youth Congress, Apr 12, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Key Pittman to Joseph Cadden, Apr 14, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to I. R. Barnes, clerk to House Committee on Foreign Relations, Apr 19, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from Joseph Cadden to I. R. Barnes, Apr 18, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from I. R. Barnes to Joseph Cadden, Apr 18, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from I. R. Barnes to Joseph Cadden, Apr 13, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Duplicate telegraph from I. R. Barnes to Joseph Cadden, Apr 18, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Senator Key Pittman to Joseph Cadden, Apr 27, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Knute Hill to Joseph Cadden, May 3, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Knute Hill, Apr 29, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Representative Matthew A. Dunn to Joseph Cadden, May 3, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Matthew A. Dunn, Apr 29, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Representative Sol Bloom to Joseph Cadden, May 9, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Sol Bloom, Apr 28, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator William H. King, Sep 21, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Wmillard E. Tydings, Sep 22, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Albert J. Engel, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative John M. Houston, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Harry R. Sheppard, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Malcolm C. Tarver, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Butler B. Haret, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Frank B. Keefe, Jan 18, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Representative William M. Colmer to Frances M. Williams, Jan 19, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Frances M. Williams to Representative William M. Colmer, Mar 2, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Congressman Wright Patman, Feb 28, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Telegram from Jack McFall to Joseph Cadden, Feb 29, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Jack McFall, Mar 1, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to George W. Norris, Mar 19, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Telegram from Senator Walter F. George to Joseph Cadden, Jan 30, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator Arthur Capper, Jan 31, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Charles A. Murray, secretary to Committee on Education and Labor, to Joseph Cadden, Jan 31, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Senator James E. Murray, Jan 31, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Joseph Cadden to Representative Robert L. Doughton, May 14, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Barron K. Grier, clerk to Committee on Ways and Means, to Joseph Cadden, May 16, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from Joseph Cadden to Barron K. Grier, May 14, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from Frances M. Williams to Representative Frances Walter, Jun 9, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Telegraph from Frances M. Williams to Edith N. Johnson, Jun 16, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Edith N. Johnson to Frances M. Williams, Jun 16, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Elbert D. Thomas to Frances M. Williams, Aug 6, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Edward E. Strong to Senator Sheridan Downey, Sep 10, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Edward E. Strong to Senator Robert R. Reynolds, Sep 10, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Edward E. Strong to Senator Lister Hill, Sep 10, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Response letter from Senator Sheridan Downey to Edward E. Strong, Sep 11, 1941 (Box 1)
  - 15 original letters and 6 carbon, circa 1939-1941 (Box 1)
- Press Correspondence: Letters to the Editor, Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Government Correspondence and Publications: Treasury Department Correspondence; Department of Justice Correspondence; State Department Correspondence; State Department Press Release; Secretary of Commerce Correspondence; Attorney General Correspondence; White House Stationery; Weekly List of Selected United States Gov't Publications, No. 13, 15, 16; Pamphlet: Strengthening the National Defense, 1941 (Box 1)
- Mayor La Guardia + other correspondence: La Guardia/Mayor's Office correspondence; Hamilton House Junior League; Other Correspondence; Liberal Survey, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Broadcasting Correspondence: Correspondence; Broadcasting Schedule; American Youth Commission broadcast times; Cooperation b/n Rural and Urban Youth essays, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Congressional Bills: Congressional Record; Press Releases; Pamphlets; Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Anti-Poll Tax Documents: Flyers; Bulletin; Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Financial Documents: Petty Cash; Bills/Invoices; Dunning letters from service providers; Expense Reports/notes; Ledgers/Monetary Reports; Tax Statement; Donations; Checks, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Lina Odena Fund: Correspondence; Bulletins, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Inter-American Student Conference: Questionnaires (Completed, in Spanish); Blank Questionnaire; Correspondence; Information Packet/Pamphlets, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Correspondence between American Countries in reference to Inter-American Student Conference: Argentina; Cuba; Mexico; Panama; Brazil; Ecuador; Chile; Costa Rica; Dominican Republic; Colombia; Jamaica; Paraguay; Uruguay; Nicaragua; Guatemala; Honduras; Bolivia; El Salvador; Venezuela; Puerto Rico, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Inter-American Press Clippings: Photos (Frances Williams pictured with other ppl); Banquet Invitation (Spanish), 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Latin/South American Newspapers: Cultura (Ano 13, No. 112 + Ano 14, No 115) 2 issues; Boletim da C.E.B (Ano 4, No 24-26 +Ano 4, No 30-32 + Ano 5, No 33-36); Avanzada (Ano 1, no 16 + No 21 + No 24 + No 25 + No 26); Juventud de Espana (Ano 1 No. 1 + Ano 2 No. 11, 12, 14, 15, 16, 18, 20); O Lider (Ano 1 No. 1); AECI (Asociacion Estudiantil de Correspondencia Interamericana) (Ano 1 No. 1); FEC Cartel (Ano 1 No 19); Unidade; Roja Estrelia (Ano 14); La Defensa (Ano 5, No 383); Espana Democratica (Ano 5, No 207), 1941-1942 (Box 1)
- Latin/South American Magazines: Revista Agronomica (Ano 5, No 45), 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Latin/South American Pamphlets: Unidos por Cuba y la Juventud; U.F.E.H. Bulletin (No. 1 and 2); Manifiesto de la Union Federal de Estudiantes Hispanos; Camp Vernet Press Release (In English), 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Bulletins/Newsletters: Newscast; University Labor Federation Bulletin, No. 7-9, 11-16; Youth for Victory, No.1; Department of Labor; Labor Information Bulletin, Volume 8, No 3; Division of Public Contracts, Bulletins 231-234, 1941 (Box 1)
- Fundraising: Letters (none signed); Pamphlets; Return cards, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Studies, Essays, Papers: AYC Creed; Vassar Peace Pact; Civil Liberties Manual Draft/Documents; Miscellaneous Documentation, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Publicity Proposals/Press Releases, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
- Foreign Policy Association: Subscription pamphlets; Foreign Policy reports and bulletins; Form Letters; Membership forms for students; Timeline: Teachers Institute on International Affairs; Branch Officers and Chairmen of Special Committees; Institute on International Affairs Flyers; Press Releases; Other Documentation: Flyers/Bulletins/Questionnaires; Event Flyers and Invitations, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- American Peace Mobilization: Correspondence; Press Release; Pamphlets/posters; Meeting minutes and information items, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- New York Conference for Inalienable Rights: Correspondence; Bulletins/Newsletters; Press Release/Statement, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Posters, Logos, Miscellaneous Prints, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- International Youth Congress (Held in Mexico City), 1941 (Box 2)
- More International Youth Congress Correspondence and Roster, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Event Correspondence, Flyers, and Programs, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- New York Peace Committee for April 6th Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Rural Youth Commission: Rural Outlook Newsletter; Meeting Minutes; Press releases/Misc Documentation; Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Canadian Youth Congress: Correspondence; Pamphlets/Petitions/Other Documentation, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Youth Congresses/Councils/Clubs of NYC/NY and surrounding areas: East Side Youth Congress, Remembering Congressman Edelstein bulletin; Park West Youth Congress; Brooklyn Youth Federation; Bay Ridge Youth Council; West Side Youth Council; Harlem Youth Congress; Crown Heights Youth Council; East Side Federation of Social Clubs; New Haven Conference of Youth, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Pamphlets Published by American Youth Congress, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Pamphlets Published outside of American Youth Congress, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Other Youth Organizations: American Jewish Congress; American Student Union; California Youth Legislature; International Student Services; New York National Youth Association (N.Y.A.); Student Defenders of Democracy; Young Men's Vocational Foundation; Young Austria in Great Britain; Youth Relief and Refugee Council; YWCA/YMCA; Massachusetts Youth Council; American Youth Congress of Chicago; World Student Association; New York Youth Congress; Southern Negro Youth Congress, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Civil Rights Organizations: NAACP; American Committee Protection of Foreign Born; National Committee for People's Rights; National Federation for Constitutional Liberties; Civil Liberties Commission; Miscellaneous Organizations; International Labor Defense; American Labor Party, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
- Military Welfare (Several Organizations): Army Welfare Committee, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- Publications - Newspapers: University Forward (Volume 3, No 11, Volume 4, Nos 13 + 17, Volume 7); On Dit (Volume 11, Nos 1, 3-8); University of Cape Town (Volume VII, No 13 + 14); Salient (Volume 4, No 1); In Fact (Volume III, No 25); The Quoddy Eagle (Volume III, No 13); Random Bulletins/Newspaper Clippings, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- International Correspondence/Documentation: Australia/New Zealand; Africa; Palestine; Asia; India (including letter from Rajni Patel); Correspondence; Britain/International Youth Rally in London; France; Norway; Sweden; USSR, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- Correspondence Regarding World Youth Congress, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- Annual Youth Congresses: Correspondence; Flyers and Pamphlets; Manual, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- American Youth Congress Bulletins and Meeting Minutes, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- American Youth Congress National Office: Correspondence, Flyers/Pamphlets, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- American Youth Fellowship Fund: Press Releases, Flyers/Pamphlets, Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- Research on American Youth Congress: Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
- Mr. Youth Goes to Washington (American Youth Congress Institute), Feb 9-12, 1940 (Box 3)
- Interfaith Commission, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Interfaith Commission, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Greetings: Telegrams, Letters, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Trade Union: Pamphlets, Flyers, Bulletins, Press Releases, Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Teachers Union: Pamphlets/Flyers, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Handwritten Notes/Checklists, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Frances Williams: Map of Salzburg, Form Letters, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Mailing Lists, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Revolutionary War School Project, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Youth, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Speakers Service, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- The People's Lobby + American Youth Congress Stationery, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Christian Missionary Society, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- United American Artists Anti-War Protest, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- United States Junior Chamber of Commerce, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Roswell Perry Rosengren, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- United Synagogue of America, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Housing, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Other Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)
- Other Posters, Flyers, and Pamphlets, 1930s-1940s (Box 4)